Okay, GI pathology, the very first section that we're going to talk about is oral cavity.
The first lesion that we want to discuss is cleft, lip, and palate.
This is a full thickness defect of the lip and or the palate.
Usually a cleft, lip, and palate will occur together.
What's important here and perhaps the highest yield on this slide is the fact that the cleft, lip, and palate is due to failure of facial prominences to fuse.
Now remember that the way by which the face forms is that you have this prominence that grows from the top and then two that grow from the side and two that come from above.
And all of these five prominences, they fuse, and that eventually leads to formation of the face.
So if there's failure of those prominences to fuse, that can result in cleft, lip, and palate.
And so the high yield here is the fact that there's this embryology tie-in.
So I would remember that the facial prominences are very important in this particular disorder.
Here's what a cleft, lip, and palate looks like.
We're all familiar with this image, and this is a classic image here of a cleft lip, and underlying it is most likely a cleft palate.
Aphthous ulcer is a lesion that can occur on the oral mucosa.
It's a superficial ulceration that is painful.
It arises in relation to stress, often resolved spontaneously, but it can recur.
For anyone who has this or who experiences this, you know how painful it can be, and you realize that it will resolve and sometimes can recur.
It's characterized by a grayish base surrounded by erythema, and this is what it looks like.
You can clearly see that there's this grayish base, and it's surrounded by all of this erythema.
Now this grayish base actually represents granulation tissue.
One of the derivative syndromes concerning aphthous ulcers is Bissett syndrome, in which patients get recurrent aphthous ulcers plus genital ulcers and uveitis,
so that they may have some sort of visual disturbance.
So this is the triad, it's recurrent aphthous ulcers plus genital ulcers and uveitis.
It's actually due to immune complex vasculitis involving the small blood vessels.
We don't know the exact etiology.
It may be seen after a viral infection, but again, we don't know the exact etiology.
Oral herpes is when you have vesicles involving the oral mucosa.
These vesicles usually rupture, which then results in a shallow, painful red ulcer.
Important, it's usually due to HSV-1.
The primary infection with oral herpes occurs in childhood.
The lesion actually heals, but the virus remains dormant in the ganglia of the trigeminal nerve.
This is high yield.
Virus remains dormant in the ganglia of the trigeminal nerve.
Then what happens is that in the face of stress or sunlight or other types of stimuli,
you get reactivation of the virus, and the reactivation of the virus leads to vesicles
that usually arise on the lips and are classically called a cold sore.
And here's what a cold sore looks like.
It's this vesicle arising on the lips.
And again, that would be due to reactivation of HSV-1 virus,
which was remaining dormant in the ganglia of the trigeminal nerve.
Squamous cell carcinoma can also arise on the oral mucosa,
and this would be a malignant neoplasm of squamous cells, obviously.
Two major risk factors are going to be tobacco and alcohol.
Tobacco and alcohol, high yield, major risk factors.
The most common location within the oral mucosa is the floor of the mouth.
That's where we would most likely expect to see this cancer.
Now often, before you get squamous cell carcinoma, we can get dysplasia.
And when patients get squamous dysplasia, that often presents,
or it can present as leukoplakia or erythroplakia.
So these are precursor lesions.
Leukoplakia means white plaque.
Leuco means white, and plakia means plaque.
And when a patient has leukoplakia, you have to worry about squamous dysplasia.
Now, leukoplakia doesn't necessarily equal squamous cell dysplasia,
but it's something that you have to be concerned with when you see leukoplakia.
Basically, when you see leukoplakia, the way by which you kind of run through the workup in your mind
is that if you've got a patient with leukoplakia,
the very first thing that you might want to do is take a tongue depressor and try to scrape it away.
If you can scrape away that white plaque, then that indicates that you're dealing with oral candidiasis.
It's easily scraped away, and it's usually seen in immunocompromised patients.
Another thing that can give you a white plaque is something called hairy leukoplakia.
This is where you get a very shaggy, rough patch on the lateral tongue.
Lateral tongue is high yield, and that's important to know.
So, hairy leukoplakia is classically on the lateral aspect of the tongue,
and it gives you this rough, shaggy patch.
Now, important to know that it's due to EBV.
Again, important to know due to EBV.
Associated with an immunocompromised state,
usually seen in patients in an immunocompromised state,
and it only represents hyperplasia of the squamous mucosa.
There is no dysplasia there.
So, those are two things that you need to be able to distinguish from true leukoplakia.
That is, oral candidiasis and hairy leukoplakia.
When a patient has leukoplakia,
and if you're concerned that it might represent squamous dysplasia,
of course, a biopsy could be performed,
and you can do the biopsy to rule out carcinoma.
Now, erythroplakia refers to a red plaque, erythro, red, and plakia plaque.
When you have erythroplakia,
that indicates that you have vascularized leukoplakia,
meaning you have leukoplakia with a lot of blood vessels.
And that suggests that there might be some new blood vessel growth,
like angiogenesis,
and that would be highly suggestive of squamous dysplasia.
So, if I asked you which one of the following,
leukoplakia or erythroplakia,
is more suggestive of squamous dysplasia,
the answer would be erythroplakia.
So, that's very important to bear in mind.
Here's a classic picture of oral candidiasis.
This looks like a white kind of plaque,
but you would easily be able to scrape this away with a tongue depressor,
and the patient would clearly have a history of being in an immunocompromised state.
And that concludes this particular section on the oral mucosa.
The next section is the salivary gland.